René L Warren

warrenlr@gmail.com

778 . 386 . 4192

www.renewarren.ca

Narrative:

I am a <u>Coordinator</u> and <u>Researcher</u> with over 20 years experience in biotechnology, genomics and computing research. I have played a central role in managing the bioinformatics of large international collaborations to decrypt the genomes of *Rhodococus*, Cryptococcus, spruce and bullfrog. I developed the first program for genome assembly with then emerging short DNA sequences and pioneered the development of genomics technologies that enabled the discovery of *Fusobacterium* in colon cancer, one of *Time Magazine*'s top ten medical breakthrough of 2011.

I currently lead the BC Genome Sciences Centre's bioinformatics technology lab high-performance computing group and I am eager to take on additional challenges and leadership.

Language spoken and written: Français and English

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Sep 2010 – Present

Coordinator

BC Cancer Agency – Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Provide project leadership, expertise, guidance
- · Plan / coordinate group activities
- Supervise / mentor biologists and programmers
- Report progress
- Write research grant proposals
- Interview candidates / teach and train personnel

Jan 2002 – Mar 2010

Computational Biologist

BC Cancer Agency – Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- · Lead bioinformatics software R&D
- Published research in reputed journals / international conferences
- Developed marketing (web portals / news release)
- Supervised a team of biologists and programmers
- Interviewed job candidates, taught and trained employees

Jan 2000 – Dec 2001

Technical Officer

National Research Council - Biotechnology Research Institute, Montreal QC

- Co-engineered a system for regulating gene expression in cells
- Designed, fabricated and tested components of the DNA "gene switch"
- · Work led to a patent, technology sold to company
- Integrated technology in other systems (viral, cell)

EDUCATION

Sep 2005 – Jun 2006	People and Project Management Courses Provincial Health Services Authority of British Columbia, Canada
Sep 2000 – Dec 2001	Computer Science Courses Concordia University, Montréal, Canada
Jun 1997 – Aug 1999	MSc Biochemistry & Molecular Biology University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada Studies of the regulation of rod photoreceptors cGMP-gated channels
Sep 1994 – May 1997	BSc Biochemistry , dean Honour list mention in 1995 and 1996 Université de Montréal, Montréal, Canada Structure-function studies of the transcription factor Nkx2-5

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

2015, 16	Recipient of the John Jambor Knowledge Fund
2011	Interviewed by NTN24 channel for Fusobacterium discovery colon cancer
2009	Interviewed by Genome Technology to discuss next-generation sequencing
2007	Interviewed by GenomeWeb for the development of SSAKE
1998	UBC Graduate Fellowship awarded for MSc
1997	Fonds de la Recherche en Santé Québec (FRSQ) awarded for BSc
1996	Bursary from FRSQ for BSc honour's research project
1995	Worked at NASA to coordinate the crystallization of proteins under
	microgravity [CMIX-4 payload, space shuttle Endeavour]

PRESENTATIONS (International conferences, selected from 12)

Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, Dublin UK/Orlando USA - talks
Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing, Kona, Hawaii, USA – posters
Sequencing, Finishing and Analysis in the Future, Santa Fe USA – talk
Advances in Genome Biology and Technology, Marco Island USA – poster
Synthetic Biology 3.0 conference, Zürich, Switzerland – talk

PUBLICATIONS (selected from over 40)

Warren RL, *et al.* (2015) LINKS: Scalable, alignment-free scaffolding of draft genomes with long reads. GigaScience 4:35

Warren RL, et al. (2013) Co-occurrence of anaerobic bacteria in colorectal carcinomas. Microbiome. 1:16
Warren RL, et al. (2012) Derivation of HLA types from shotgun sequence datasets. Genome Med. 4:95
Castellarin M*, Warren RL*, et al. (2012) Fusobacterium nucleatum infection is prevalent in human colorectal carcinoma. Genome Res. 22:299-306 *equal contributions

Warren RL, et al. (2007) Assembling millions of short DNA sequences using SSAKE. Bioinfo. 23:500 E Allen-Vercoe, R Holt, R Moore, R Warren. Detection of fusobacterium in a gastrointestinal sample to diagnose gastrointestinal cancer. US Patent App. 13/877,421 / WO Patent 2,012,045,150

REFERENCES

Available upon request